Finding Aid for Harry A. Towsley Papers 1876-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harry A. Towsley papers 1876-1990
Towsley, Harry A.
Pediatrician, professor and philanthropist, joined University of Michigan Dept. of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases in 1934, and served with the 298th General Hospital Unit during World War II. Papers include medical school lecture notes, class of 1931 files, medical research files; correspondence, histories, photographs and motion pictures relating to the 298th General Hospital Unit, family history materials including Frank A. Towsley's diary, 1876, and family correspondence, 1878-1926 and photographs.
86981 Aa 2
9.0 linear feet
1 oversize folders
9 film reels
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Dr. Harry A. Towsley (Donor No. 4289 ) donated 298th General Hospital files in 1985. Additional records were received from the Towsley estate in 1993 and 1994.
The collection is open for research.
Harry Albert Towsley (1905-1993), pediatrician, professor, and philanthropist, was born September 15, 1905, in Midland, Michigan, the son of Dr. Frank A. and Harriet Sias Towsley. After graduating from Midland High School in 1922, he attended Kalamazoo College (1922-1923), Michigan State University (1923-1924), and the University of Michigan (1925-1927). In 1931, he earned his medical degree from the University of Michigan and was a member of Alpha Kappa Kappa, the professional medical fraternity. His training included stints as a rotating intern and assistant resident at the University Hospital, 1931-1933, and resident in the Department of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases 1933-1934. He spent parts of 1933 and 1934 observing and studying pediatric facilities in Boston, Chicago, Cincinnati, New York, St. Louis, and Great Britain.
In 1934, he was appointed as an instructor in the Department of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases and became assistant professor in 1941. During this time he recognized the potential value of technology in teaching and continuing education and was quick to utilize film as an educational medium, collaborating on the production of several nationally distributed films.
His instructional career was interrupted by military service with the University of Michigan affiliated 298th General Hospital during World War II. The unit was activated on June 27, 1942, and spent thirty-six months overseas operating hospitals in Bristol, England; Cherbourg, France; and Liege, Belgium, before leaving Europe on September 23, 1945. Towsley enlisted as a major in 1942, and was promoted to lt. colonel, serving as chief, Division of Communicable Diseases and Chief, Laboratory Services. He was also the unit historian.
Following his return from military service he assumed direction of the affiliated hospital program of the Department of Postgraduate Medicine, directing the newly developed program of decentralized graduate medical instruction and was coordinator of extramural activities. During this period he carried the dual titles of associate professor of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases and associate professor in the Department of Postgraduate Medicine.
In 1954, he was named associate director of the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and subsequently became chairman in 1967, following the death of John M. Sheldon. Towsley served as chairman of the department until his retirement in 1971.
Dr. Towsley was active in numerous professional organizations and civic groups. He was a fellow and diplomat of the American Academy of Pediatrics and served as chairman of the subcommittee on Postgraduate Education, and was president of the Academy during 1964-65. On the state level he was active in the Michigan State Medical Society as a member of the Iodized Salt Committee and chairman of the Committee on Postgraduate Medical Education. He was also a member of the Washtenaw County Medical Society, serving as president in 1948. In 1970, he was elected into the Michigan Health Council Hall of Fame.
He also served on several boards, including the Michigan Foundation for Medical and Health Education, Michigan United Fund, and American Social Health Association. On the community front he was active as a member of the Michigan Children's Aid Society, Ann Arbor Board of Health, Ann Arbor Community Chest, and Chamber of Commerce Board of Directors.
At the University of Michigan he was involved in numerous committees and organizations, including the Alumni Association, Development Council (he chaired the Foundation Relations Committee from 1973 to 1980), and the University Committee on Broadcasting, 1954-1971. Within the Medical Center he was on the Student Aid Committee, and was a member and chairman of the Audiovisual Committee, 1946-1971. He was also editor of the Medical Center Journal from 1964 to 1972.
On August 14, 1932, he married Margaret Dow (1906-1994), daughter of the founder of the Dow Chemical Company. Mrs. Towsley received her bachelor degree from the University of Michigan in 1928 and a master's from Columbia University in 1930. She was a community leader whose accomplishments included election to the Ann Arbor City Council, and the founding of the Children's Play School in 1935. In 1960, the couple established the Harry A. and Margaret D. Towsley Foundation, a private charitable foundation designed to assist religious, educational, charitable and scientific organizations with their programs. The foundation also worked for the prevention of cruelty to children. The majority of the funds have been distributed in the state of Michigan, primarily in the Ann Arbor area. Among the foundation's significant donations to the University of Michigan were the Towsley Center for Continuing Medical Education, and major gifts to the Wiley T. Buchanon Research Fund and the Kellogg Eye Center. The Towsleys had five daughters: Margaret Ann (Reicker), Janice Elizabeth (Poteat), Judith Dow (Alexander), Harriet Susan (Inglish), and Grace Lynn (Hamblin).
Dr. Harry A. Towsley died at his home on March 31, 1993. Margaret Dow Towsley died of a stroke May 2, 1994.
The papers of Harry A. Towsley provide a broad overview of the many facets of his career, including his medical education at the University of Michigan, his service with the 298th General Hospital during World War II, and his professional career as a pediatrician and educator. The collection is arranged in eleven series as follows: Biographical Material; Correspondence; Family History; Foundation Relations Committee Files; General Files; Iodine and Goiter Research; Pediatric Files; Student Notes; Reunion Files; 298th General Hospital Records; and Films.
Subjects:
Alpha Kappa Kappa Fraternity. Alpha Iota Chapter (University of Michigan); Goiter.; Hospitals.; Iodine.; Medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Pediatrics.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Towsley, Harry A.; Towsley family.; United States. Army. General Hospital Unit, 298th.; University of Michigan. Development Council.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. Medical School. Class of 1931.; World War, 1939-1945--Medical care.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Alpha Kappa Kappa Fraternity. Alpha Iota Chapter (University of Michigan); Fishing.; Hospitals.; Hunting.; Medical aspects of war.; Military facilities.; Military life.; Nurses.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Towsley, Harry A.; United States. Army. General Hospital Unit, 298th.; University of Michigan. Medical School. Class of 1931.; War damage.; Women--Military service.; World War, 1939-1945.; Towsley, Frank A., 1858-1919.; Towsley, Harry A.; Towsley, Margaret Dow, 1906-1994.; Towsley, Wilbur D., 1897-1971.
Contributors:
Towsley, Frank A., 1858-1919.; Towsley, Harry A.; Towsley, Margaret Dow, 1906-1994.; Towsley, Wilbur D., 1897-1971.
Genre/Form:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.; Motion pictures.; Tintypes.; Videotapes.
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Material series contains a loose collection of curriculum vitae, bibliographies, and miscellaneous articles about Harry A. Towsley and his wife, Margaret Dow Towsley. The highlight of the series is a bound volume of letters of tribute from colleagues and friends given to Towsley at his retirement in 1971.
  - Biographical Information 1948-1970 (Box 1)
    - Margaret Dow Towsley 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - "Letters of Appreciation Presented to Harry A. Towsley, M.D. on the Occasion of his Retirement" 1971, 1 volumes (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence consists of chronologically arranged outgoing letters sent by Towsley to his wife and children while he was serving overseas with the 298th General Hospital. Due to censorship restrictions, these letters, covering 1944-1945, focus mainly on aspects of daily life rather than military activity. A single file of scattered incoming correspondence, 1975-1982, offers a modest glimpse into his activities during his active retirement.
  - Correspondence (outgoing)
    - January-March, 1944 (Box 1)
    - June, 1944 (Box 1)
    - July 1944 (Box 1)
    - August, 1944 (Box 1)
    - September, 1944 (Box 1)
    - October, 1944 (Box 1)
    - November, 1944 (Box 1)
    - December, 1944 (Box 1)
    - January, 1945 (Box 1)
    - February, 1945 (Box 1)
    - March, 1945 (Box 1)
    - April, 1945 (Box 1)
    - May-July 1945 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (incoming) 1975-1982 (Box 1)
- Family History
  The Family History series offers a rich source of information on the Towsley and Sias families. Included are a variety of late 19th and early 20th century photographs of family members and friends in a variety of photographic formats (cartes-de-visites, tintypes, and snapshots). Several late 1980s photographs of Harry Towsley and his wife are also found here. Material on Wilbur D. Towsley (1897-1971), brother of Harry A. Towsley, provides insight into the life of his brother who was a physician in Midland, Michigan and includes photographs and newspaper accounts of various hunting and fishing trips, as well as information on Wilbur's estate. Other family memorabilia includes a partial 1876 diary kept by his father, Frank A. Towsley (1858-1919), and a 1901 patent for "Stream or Current Motors."
  - Correspondence (misc.) 1878-1926 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Diary (Frank A. Towsley) 1876 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous circa 1963-1974 and n.d. (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings circa 1897-1966 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Patent "Stream or Current Motors," 1901 (Box 1)
  - Sias Family Genealogy, n.d (Box 1)
  - Wilbur D. Towsley
    - Testimonial Dinner 1960 (Box 1)
    - Estate 1971-1974 (Box 1)
    - Funeral Record 1971 (Box 1)
    - Photographs, circa 1959-1960s
      - Fishing In God's Country (notebook) 1956 (Box 1)
      - Kapuskasing Moose Hunt 1957 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Family)
    - Tintypes, 11 photographs (Box 1)
    - Cartes-de-Visite Photographs, 20 photographs (Box 1)
    - Cabinet Photographs (16) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Portraits and Snapshots, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Harry and Margaret Towsley)
    - Group Portraits (Harry Towsley) (Box 1)
    - Harry and Margaret Towsley (posed and candid) (Box 1)
- Foundation Relations Committee Files
  The Foundation Relations Committee Files contains records from Towsley's tenure as a member of the University of Michigan Development Council Foundation Relations Committee which he chaired from 1973 to 1980. His knowledge gained from operating the Harry A. and Margaret D. Towsley Foundation is apparent in these chronologically arranged records.
  - University of Michigan Development Council (Box 2)
    - Board of Directors 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Foundation Relations Committee
      - 1974, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1975, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Nominating Committee 1970-1981, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - School and College Fundraising Study Committee 1971-1972 (Box 2)
- General Files
  A brief collection of alphabetically arranged General Files contains documentation relating to his professional and personal activities. Of note are files relating to the professional medical fraternity Alpha Kappa Kappa (including photographs of the fraternity house on 1315 Hill Street), and some of his early work with audio-visual education from 1938 to 1941.
  - Alpha Kappa Kappa 1946-1947, 1951-1978, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Block, George 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - DeJong (Russell) Symposium 1976 (Box 2)
  - Dingman (Reed) Retirement 1975 (Box 2)
  - Galens Scholarship Fund 1940 (Box 2)
  - Harry A. and Margeret D. Towsley Foundation 1959-1976, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Health Council 1968-1970 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous "Stuff & Nonsense" circa 1940s-1981 (Box 2)
  - Photographic Committee 1938-1941 (Box 2)
  - Political Campaigns
    - Gerald Ford, Marvin Esch 1976 (Box 2)
    - General 1978 (Box 2)
    - Jim Brickley for Governor 1982 (Box 2)
  - Pollard, H. Marvin 1935, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Requests for Motion Pictures 1938-1939 (Box 2)
  - Rossiter Fund 1971-1977 (Box 2)
  - Snider, Robert J. (Class of 1916 re: WW I experiences) (Box 2)
  - University Replacement Hospital 1981 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw County Community College 1964 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw County United Fund 1971 (Box 2)
- Iodine and Goiter Research
  The Iodine and Goiter Research series is a chronologically arranged file relating to his committee service and research interest in Iodine and the prevention of goiter. Material includes research files, writings, correspondence, and reprints.
  - Iodization of Salt 1924 (Box 3)
  - Michigan State Medical Society (Iodized Salt Committee)
    - Abstracted Review of the Literature Pertaining to the Use of Iodized Salt Since Its Inception in Michigan (1924-1935) 1935
      - Abstracts 1935 (Box 3)
      - Reprints 1923-1951, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Thyroid Survey 1935 (Box 3)
    - Incidence of Enlarged Thymus Following Prenatal Use of Iodized Salt circa 1936 (Box 3)
    - Possible Relationship of Thymic Hyperplasia and Incidence of Goiter in Michigan circa 1936 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Memorandums 1939-1970, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - American Public Health Association (Committee on Endemic Goiter)
    - Correspondence 1941, 1945-1946, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Minutes of Initial and Second Meeting 1941-1942, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Broadcasting Service Talk on Iodized Salt, n.d (Box 3)
  - Michigan Television--Iodine and Goiter 1953 (Box 3)
  - Fortification of Milk 1953-1955 (Box 3)
  - Matrovinovic, Josip 1965-1983 (Box 3)
  - Thyroid Workshop 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Michigan in the Goiter Belt (Talk) 1979 (Box 3)
- Pediatric Files
  Pediatric Files consists of two subseries: Pediatric Research and Studies and Pediatric Societies. The first subseries is an alphabetically arranged collection of research notes and writings on a variety of pediatric subjects. The second subseries documents his professional involvement with the American Academy of Pediatrics, including his term as president, 1964-65. Files of this professional society include correspondence with United Kingdom pediatricians Wilfrid Sheldon and Arthur G. "Pop" Watkins, and Towsley's successful effort to secure honorary membership in the organization for these two doctors.
  - Pediatric Research and Studies
    - "The Constipated Infant," 1955 (Box 4)
    - Death During Anesthesia in Children 1935-1949 (Box 4)
    - Dysostosis Multiplay circa 1949 (Box 4)
    - Fetal Respiratory Movements circa 1941 (Box 4)
    - Prophylaxis and Modification of Measels with Umbilical Cord Blood Plasma 1938 (Box 4)
    - Pseudo Hypertrophic Muscular Disease and Glycine circa 1939, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Respiratory Distress circa 1949 (Box 4)
    - Scarlet Fever Study circa 1933-1934, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Stevens-Johnson Syndrome circa 1951 (Box 4)
    - Study of Intrauterine Oxygen Exchange, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1938 n.d. (Box 4)
  - Pediatric Societies (American Academy of Pediatrics)
    - Award 1962 (Box 4)
    - Continuing Education 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Founders Day Awards 1980 (Box 4)
    - Honorary Memberships (Wilfrid Sheldon and Arthur G. "Pop" Watkins) 1964-1966
      - Wilfrid Sheldon Correspondence 1957-1959 (Box 4)
      - Arthur G. Watkins Correspondence 1958-1962 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Chapter
      - 1951-1952 (Box 4)
      - 1968-1969, 1984 (Box 4)
    - PREP Committee (Pediatric Research, Education and Practice) 1961-1965, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Presidential Records 1964-1966, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Talk, "Can the Practicing Physician Keep Up?" 1968 (Box 4)
- Student Notes
  Student Notes documents Towsley's medical education and training. Material includes lecture notes, two term papers, and several notebooks in which he recorded his observations and comments during his internship and residency training, including the year of travel spent observing pediatric facilities in America and Great Britain.
  - Dermatology circa 1929-1931, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Neurology circa 1929 (Box 4)
  - Pathology 1929-1930, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Pediatrics 1929-1930 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Notes circa 1929-1931, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Term Papers
    - The Aesculapian Temple of Healing 1929 (Box 4)
    - Osteogenic Tumors (Surgery Thesis) 1931 (Box 4)
  - Notebooks (includes residencies) circa 1929-1933, 6 volumes (Box 4)
- Reunion Files (Medical School Class of 1931)
  The series Reunion Files consists of chronologically arranged files documenting the lives of Towsley and fellow members of the University of Michigan Medical School class of 1931. Beyond the usual reunion mechanics this series includes questionnaires (1941, 1966), correspondence, and photographs which together richly illustrated the careers and lives of this particular class.
  - Frederick G. Novy Fellowship Fund 1936-1940 (Box 5)
  - 10th Reunion 1941
    - Questionnaires 1941 (Box 5)
    - Information Cards (graduates) circa 1941-1953 (Box 5)
    - Information Cards (non-graduates) circa 1941 (Box 5)
  - Third Triennial Reunion 1947 (Box 5)
  - Medical School Centennial Reunion 1950 (Box 5)
  - Fifth Triennial Reunion 1953 (Box 5)
  - 25th Reunion and Scholarship Fund 1956-1959 (Box 5)
  - Reunion and Directory 1959 (Box 5)
  - 30th Reunion 1960-1964 (Box 5)
  - 35th Reunion 1966-1968 (Box 5)
  - 35th and 40th Reunions
    - A-B 1966, 1971 (Box 5)
    - C-G 1966, 1971 (Box 5)
    - H 1966, 1971 (Box 5)
    - J-P 1966, 1971 (Box 5)
    - R-S 1966, 1971 (Box 5)
    - T-Z 1966, 1971 (Box 5)
  - 45th Reunion 1976 (Box 5)
  - 50th Reunion 1981, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1931, 1956, 1976, 1981 (Box 5)
- 298th General Hospital Records
  The strength of the collection rests in the 298th General Hospital Records. These records fully document this unit from inception through deactivation. The unit's affiliation with the university is well documented through correspondence and records of the University of Michigan Affiliated Medical Unit Welfare Association. Also included are three highly detailed annual reports recounting the history of the unit from 1943 to 1945. Illustrations in these volumes combined with a collection of snapshots document all facets of life at an army hospital from the unusual to the mundane, including a series of photographs depicting the Normandy region in France in the months following the massive D-Day landings.
  - Histories and Related Material
    - General Histories 1944-1948 (Box 6)
    - Diaries 1944-1945 (Box 6)
    - Historian's Reports
      - July 1943-April 1944 (Box 6)
      - June-August 1945 (Box 6)
    - Nursing History 1942-1945 (Box 6)
    - Section Histories 1945 (Box 6)
    - Social History and Roster of Enlisted Men 1944-1945 (Box 6)
  - Administrative
    - Annual Reports (include photographs)
      - 1943, 211 pages; 60 photographs (Box 6)
      - 1944, 309 pages (Box 6)
      - 1945, 260 pages; 79 photographs (Box 6)
    - Commanding Officer's Report January-June, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1943, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Records Jacket, Harry A. Towsley 1942-1945 (Box 6)
    - Standardization Manual (w/ photos), circa 1943 (Box 6)
    - Surgical Service Report 1944 (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan Affiliated Medical Unit Welfare Association 1942-1945, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - 1940 (Box 6)
    - 1941 (Box 6)
    - 1942-1943 (Box 6)
    - 1947-1952 (Box 6)
  - Printed Material
    - Guides to Bristol, England 1938 and Liege, Belgium, 1939, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Maps 1942, 1944 (Box 6)
    - Stars and Stripes, 1945 (Box 6)
    - University Hospital Bulletin (various issues concerning 298th), 1942-1945 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Reunion (25th Anniversary of Activation) 1967 (Box 6)
    - "Frenchay Revisited, 1942-1992," by Lois White Monroe 1992 (Box 6)
    - 50th Anniversary September 1992 (Box 7)
    - Artifacts (Box 7)
      (pieces removed from a "buzz bomb" crater near the 298th, January 10, 1945)
  - Photographs
    (see also: Films)
    - Aerial Views (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Snapshots
      - 298th Departing from Ann Arbor 1942 (Box 7)
      - Airplanes (Box 7)
      - Ambulances and Other vehicles (Box 7)
      - Bivouac (Box 7)
      - Cemeteries (Box 7)
      - General Camp Scenes, 2 envelopes (Box 7)
      - German Prisoners of War (Box 7)
      - Groups (formal) (Box 7)
      - Groups (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
      - Hospital Patients (Box 7)
      - Hospital Train (Box 7)
      - Individuals (Box 7)
      - Interiors (Box 7)
      - Mess Operations (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      - Normandy Scenes (July 1944) (Box 7)
      - Officer Groups (Box 7)
      - Queen Mary's Visit (Box 7)
      - Recreation/Athletics (Box 7)
      - "Tourist Views" (Box 7)
      - Towsley, Harry A (Box 7)
      - V1 "Buzz Bomb" Rockets (Box 7)
      - War Damage (Box 7)
      - Weddings (Box 7)
      - Winter Scenes (Box 7)
    - Glass Slides (Box 7)
- Films and Videotapes
  The Films series includes 16mm motion pictures primarily taken by Towsley or produced by him for the Medical School. The films date from 1934 to 1969, and include both color and black and white footage in reel sizes ranging from a few feet to nearly 1,000 feet. The majority of the films are silent. Footage of pediatric patients, contagious disease cases, and congenital abnormalities appears to have been used for research and teaching. Subjects include the 298th General Hospital during training and deployment, pediatric patients, infectious diseases, skin diseases, a 1940 Galens parody of Adolf Hitler, and miscellaneous home movies.
  - Videotape (VHS), 50th Anniversary September 1992 (Box 8)
  - Films, 50 foot reels
    - Congenital Deformities, 2 reels (Box 8)
    - Galens Party (UM Fresh Air Camp) 1940 (Box 8)
    - Successful Revaccinations (Box 8)
  - Films, 100 foot reels
    - Alumni Reunion 1940 (Box 8)
    - Baby Girl Durham 1956 (Box 8)
    - Dr. Furstenberg and Family (Box 8)
    - Galens Shovel 1940 (Box 8)
    - High School Football and Golf circa 1942 (Box 8)
    - "Growing Baby" (Raw Footage) 1953, 10 reels (Box 8)
    - Pediatric Cases circa 1940s, 9 reels (Box 8)
    - Polio Sarnoff Machine undated (Box 8)
    - Rabbitt Tests circa 1940, 2 reels (Box 8)
    - Rheumatic Arthritis circa 1949 (Box 8)
  - Films, 400 foot reels
    - Diagnosis and Treatment of Infectious Disease (Mead Johnson & Co.)
      - Obstructive Laryngitis (Box 8)
      - Tuberculosis in Childhood (Box 8)
    - Ice Storm and Tulips 1940 (Box 8)
    - Leeds Rumpel Phenomenon (Box 8)
    - London-New York 1934-1935 (includes Dr. Sheldon) (Box 8)
    - Nursery School 1937 (Box 8)
    - 298th General Hospital, 3 reels (Box 8)
    - University of Michigan Baby Film (Box 8)
      (see also: outsize reels)
    - Congenital Abnormalities (Box 9)
    - Congenital Diseases (Box 9)
    - Contagious Diseases (Box 9)
    - Medical Curiosities circa 1935 (Box 9)
    - Neurological Disorders (Box 9)